

  <othercredit role="proofreader">
    <firstname>FIX</firstname>
    <surname>ME!</surname>
  </othercredit>
  <othercredit role="illustrator">
    <firstname>Rebecca</firstname>
    <surname>Demarest</surname>
  </othercredit>

  <!-- All rights reserved. -->

  <publisher>
    <publishername>O’Reilly Media, Inc.    </publishername>
    <address format="linespecific">
      <street>1005 Gravenstein Highway North</street>
      <city>Sebastopol</city>
      <state>CA</state>
      <postcode>95472</postcode>
    </address>
  </publisher>

  <legalnotice role="printlocation">
    <para>Printed in the United States of America.</para>
  </legalnotice>

  <legalnotice role="printer">
    <para>[LSI]</para>
  </legalnotice>

  <legalnotice role="use">
    <para>O’Reilly books may be purchased for educational, business, or sales promotional use. Online editions are also available for most 
          titles (<ulink url="http://safaribooksonline.com" role="orm:hideurl:ital">http://safaribooksonline.com</ulink>). For more information, contact our corporate/institutional sales department:
          800-998-9938 or <phrase role="keep-together"><email>corporate@oreilly.com</email></phrase>.</para>
  </legalnotice>

  <legalnotice role="trademarks">
    <para>The O’Reilly logo is a registered trademark of O’Reilly Media, Inc. <emphasis>Mastering Bitcoin</emphasis>, the cover image, and related trade dress are trademarks of O’Reilly Media, Inc.
    </para>
    <para>Many of the designations used by manufacturers and sellers to distinguish
          their products are claimed as trademarks. Where those designations appear
          in this book, and O’Reilly Media, Inc. was aware of a trademark claim,
          the designations have been printed in caps or initial caps.    </para>
  </legalnotice>

  <legalnotice role="damages">
    <para>While the publisher and the author have used good faith efforts to ensure that the information and instructions contained in this work are accurate, the publisher and the author disclaim all responsibility for errors or omissions, including without limitation responsibility for damages resulting from the use of or reliance on this work. Use of the information and instructions contained in this work is at your own risk. If any code samples or other technology this work contains or describes is subject to open source licenses or the intellectual property rights of others, it is your responsibility to ensure that your use thereof complies with such licenses and/or rights. 
</para>
  </legalnotice>
<isbn>9781449374044</isbn><edition>1</edition><author><firstname>Andreas M.</firstname><surname>Antonopoulos</surname><authorblurb><para><emphasis role="strong">Andreas</emphasis> is a passionate technologist, who is well-versed in many technical subjects. He is a serial tech-entrepreneur, having launched businesses in London, New York, and California. He has earned degrees in Computer Science and Data Communications and Distributed Systems from UCL. With experience ranging from hardware and electronics to high level business and financial systems technology consulting and years as CTO/CIO/CSO in many companies — he combines authority and deep knowledge with an ability to make complex subjects easy to understand. More than 200 of his articles on security, cloud computing and data centers have been published in print and syndicated worldwide. His expertise includes Bitcoin, crypto-currencies, Information Security, Cryptography, Cloud Computing, Data Centers, Linux, Open Source and robotics software development. He also has been CISSP certified for 12 years.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
As a bitcoin entrepreneur, Andreas has founded three bitcoin businesses and launched several community open-source projects. He often writes articles and blog posts on bitcoin, is a permanent host on Let’s Talk Bitcoin and prolific public speaker at technology events. Andreas serves on the advisory boards of several bitcoin startups and serves as the Chief Security Officer of Blockchain.</para></authorblurb></author><editor><firstname>Mike</firstname><surname>Loukides</surname></editor><editor><firstname>Allyson</firstname><surname>MacDonald</surname></editor><copyright><year>2015</year><holder>Andreas M. Antonopoulos LLC.</holder></copyright><editor role="production"><firstname>Melanie</firstname><surname>Yarbrough</surname></editor><editor role="copy"><firstname>Kim</firstname><surname>Cofer</surname></editor><othercredit role="indexer"><firstname/><surname/></othercredit><othercredit role="coverdesigner"><firstname>Karen</firstname><surname>Montgomery</surname></othercredit><othercredit role="interiordesigner"><firstname>David</firstname><surname>Futato</surname></othercredit><printhistory><formalpara><title>First Edition</title><para>December, 2014</para></formalpara></printhistory><revhistory><revision><date>2014-12-01</date><revremark>First release</revremark></revision></revhistory>
